i want to share with you the reason why
i don't use javascript anymore and i
haven't used it for any real project
since
2017. i love javascript because of how
powerful it is and how powerful it makes
it developers not powerful in the sense
of speed i mean powerful in the sense of
how many things you can do with it with
javascript we can make websites we can
make mobile applications we can make
back-ends with node.js we can even make
video games among multiple other things
now the reason why javascript got so
popular is because of the web if we want
to program a website the only language
we can use is javascript there is
literally no other choice on the backend
in contrast there are many choices of
languages you can choose you can make
your backend in java or csharp or python
or rust or go among many many others in
the front end there is only one language
to choose
there's no choice it's like the only one
so we are forced to use it and since the
web absolutely exploded and browsers
became really powerful even in our own
pockets in our smartphones javascript
became the language you had to learn if
you wanted to be on the web but even
though we are grateful for javascript we
can also say that after working with it
for a couple of years you start to
notice that javascript has some weird
features some crazy ideas and sometimes
really bad design flaws the book
javascript the good parts says that all
programming languages have their fair
share of good and bad parts but
javascript especially has mostly bad or
even awful parts this could be because
as the book says javascript is a
language that was developed and released
in a hurry before it could be refined
that part is factually correct
javascript was actually created in only
10 days it was created by brendan ike
for the netscape navigator back in 1995.
when it was invented it was expected to
be used for short pieces of code it was
designed for quick uses but it grew to a
language that billion dollar companies
depend on i don't think the creator of
javascript could have imagined how big
and powerful and popular javascript
would become maybe if he knew what was
going to happen he would have spent more
time designing the language and maybe
removing or adding a couple of features
the thing with javascript is that even
if we now know what are the bad parts of
javascript we cannot just remove them
from the language javascript is on every
browser of the world it's been used by
millions and millions of websites if
something is removed from the language
it could break a lot of websites this is
why all they do now is to update
javascript they want to make javascript
better but they can only add new
features one on top of another so let me
show you a couple of examples on what i
mean when i say javascript is weird by
weird i mean unpredictable i mean not
intuitive and i mean way too permissive
javascript gives us too much freedom
let's take a look at this code for
example in javascript it is perfectly
legal and possible to take a number and
add it to a boolean even though the
operation makes no sense most languages
don't allow you to do this they will
stop you and tell you that you can't do
one plus true but javascript does not
show us an error instead it tries to
make that operation happen javascript
will take the true and it will turn it
into true in binary which is one
this is how we get the two as a result
of one plus true now it's very nice of
javascript to try to run the code even
if we are doing something done but the
problem is that most of the time when
that happens in your code if you are
doing one plus true in your code is
because something went wrong and it
would be better if javascript told you
that what you're doing logically makes
no sense instead of just trying to run
the code and this is just a tiny example
javascript is full of these sort of
query key things the biggest problem
with javascript in my opinion is that it
doesn't protect developers from our own
stupidity if we have this function that
takes two numbers and return their
multiplication when we use it all we
have to do is this the problem with
javascript is that it will also allow us
to do this
which is calling multiply without any
parameters
or also it is going to allow us to do
this
which is calling multiply with what is
for our function the wrong type now most
programming languages will not allow us
to do this at least they will tell us
that we have to call multiply function
with the right number of parameters if
we do something like this which is using
multiply with the wrong type and the
wrong number of parameters javascript
will still try to run the code in what
might result in a runtime error runtime
errors are the worst kind of errors
because they happen when your code is
already running in production they
happen when your users are using your
product they are the errors that you
hear from someone else usually your boss
or your team member and when you hear
about them it's too late because the
error already happened ideally we would
like to catch these errors before we
publish our code like for example if i
am trying to use multiply like this
which we know is going to give me
something i don't expect i would like
the language that i'm using to tell me
hey that's stupid what are you doing
check yourself and try again i would
like the language to tell me this to
show me that i'm doing something that is
wrong but javascript won't tell me this
and the reason why is because javascript
in our multiply function does not know
what the a and b parameters are supposed
to be
nowhere in this code we communicated to
javascript that a and b should only be
numbers now many of these problems will
be solved if we had a syntax to be able
to tell the javascript that a and b
should be a number and nothing else and
this is when typescript comes in
typescript is a programming language
that looks almost like javascript but it
has the syntax required to be able to
explain in advance what the types of
things are if we use typescript our
multiply function will look like this as
you can see the code didn't change so
much just a couple of extra things just
by doing that typescript will know that
a and b should be numbers so if we try
to do something like this we will see a
big error telling us that we are doing
something that we are not supposed to do
also typescript unlike javascript will
not return the number 2 if we try to do
1 plus true instead it will tell us that
this operation does not make sense and
it will show us an error so typescript
helps us against our own stupidity which
means that we can prevent runtime errors
from happening because the browsers
don't understand typescript after we
finish our typescript project and we
check that there are no errors and no
mistakes the typescript compiler will
compile the code to normal javascript
this way we can give javascript code to
the browser but we can be sure that in
that javascript code we are not doing
anything dumb that might make unexpected
box to happen so this is why i don't use
javascript anymore and i haven't for
quite some time migrating from
javascript to typescript is incredibly
simple and since i discovered typescript
i haven't looked back thanks to
typescript i am more productive now when
i write new code and build new projects
because i make less mistakes and also i
am more confident when i have to
refactor or i have to add a new feature
to an older project that is built with
typescript i feel safe because i know
typescript is going to protect me
against myself so if you are any kind of
developer i invite you to try typescript
today i invite you to learn typescript
and i invite you to do so for free with
me we just finished recording uploading
and subtitling in hangul a four hour
free tab script course in that course
we're going to go over the beauty that
is typescript they're going to
understand the benefits of typescript
i'm going to show you how typescript
allows us to do things like polymorphism
both in functional and object oriented
programming and we're also going to
learn how to migrate a javascript
project into a typescript project as
well so please click the link below all
you have to be is a developer if you
know java c sharp javascript python this
course is absolutely for you and if you
are not a developer yet but you want to
be i wouldn't recommend you starting
with typescript actually i will start
with javascript because i think newbie
developers have to suffer what we have
suffered so they appreciate typescript
later if you want to learn javascript
then also please click the link below
and there you will find a free
javascript course for you as well thank
you so much for watching let me know in
the comments what do you think about
typescript have you used it have you
stopped using it did you go back to
javascript after or you stayed in
typescript forever like i did let me
know in the comments i'm going to be
reading them right now thank you for
watching stay happy stay free eat kimchi
kamzamida salaam heyo see you on the
next one bye
you